Good morning, today's דף daf is technically קכ"ז kuf-kaf-zayin but we're on
קכ"ח kuf-kaf-ches עמוד א׳. amud aleph. One two three four five six
seven lines down, starting with שלח ליה רבי אבא לרבי יוסף. Shalach
lei Rabbi Abba le-Rabbi Yosef. The next entire דף daf is a
series of six rulings sent by רבי אבא Rabbi Abba to רבי
יוסף בר חמא. Rabbi Yosef bar Chama. רבי אבא Rabbi Abba and
רבי יוסף בר חמא Rabbi Yosef bar Chama are third generation אמוראים.
Amoraim. רבי אבא Rabbi Abba made עלייה aliyah from בבל, Bavel, he's
originally from בבל, Bavel, moved to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, and he's
sending these rulings back to his colleague רבי יוסף בר חמא. Rabbi
Yosef bar Chama.
I believe that yesterday's דף daf ended with
a Sh- maybe not. Most of it has to do with
either עדות, edut, with testimony, or inheriting property.
Okay, so שלח ליה רבי אבא לרבי יוסף בר חמא: Shalach lei
Rabbi Abba le-Rabbi Yosef bar Chama: הלכה, Halacha, גובין מן העבדים. govin
min ha-avadim. ורב נחמן אמר, Ve-Rav Nachman amar, אין גובין. ein govin.
So that's the whole ruling. For context, we'll go to the רשב"ם.
Rashbam. A lot of these don't give a lot of context- the
גמרא Gemara doesn't give a lot of context for the rulings, so
the רשב"ם Rashbam is very helpful.
גובין מן העבדים govin min ha-avadim is the דיבור המתחיל dibur hamatchil
in the רשב"ם, Rashbam, it's four lines into the widest of the
lines. רשב"ם Rashbam explains: בעל חוב שמת, Baal chov she-meit, גובה מעבדי
יתומים. gova me-avdei yetomim.
So someone who owes money who died and bequeathed slaves onto his
children, according to this ruling,
the בעל חוב, baal chov, the debtor, can be repaid, can force
the children of the deceased to pay him back from the
slaves that they inherited. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan in this report disagrees
and
says אין גובין, ein govin, says you cannot be paid back from
the slaves. That's the end of the first ruling. Second ruling: שלח
ליה רבי אבא לרבי יוסף בר חמא: Shalach lei Rabbi Abba le-Rabbi
Yosef bar Chama: הלכה, Halacha, שלישי בשני כשר. shelishi be-sheni kasher. רבא
אמר, Rava amar, אף בראשון. af be-rishon. מר בר רב אשי Mar
bar Rav Ashi אכשר באבא דאבא, achsher be-abba de-abba, ולית הלכתא ve-leit
hilcheta כמר בר רב אשי. ke-Mar bar Rav Ashi. So this is
a ruling about testimony and how close
the people giving testimony can be to one another. So you have
two brothers, ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, who have-
this is ראובן, Reuven, ראובן Reuven has one kid,
and then his son has a son. So this is ראובן's Reuven
grandson. And then שמעון Shimon also has kids.
I don't think this one matters, but that's okay. So the ruling
is
שלישי בשני כשר, shelishi be-sheni kasher, so this grandson can testify regarding
a case with this son. So ראובן's Reuven grandson, this is שלישי
shelishi because it's the third generation down from the original connection, can
testify against the son of the brother of his grandson. So I
think in English we would say that they are first cousins once
removed.
This will be- about this עדות, edut, about this kind of testimony
and how close they can be will be covered in more depth
in מסכת סנהדרין. Masechet Sanhedrin. So and then that's the original ruling,
that's what רבי אבא- Rabbi Abba that's what his דין din was.
רבא Rava comes along and says אף בראשון, af be-rishon, that the
third generation, that's this grandson of ראובן, Reuven, can testify even against
שמעון. Shimon.
Because this relationship is ראשון, rishon, this relationship is שני, sheni, שלישי.
shelishi. So the שלישי shelishi can testify against ראשון. rishon.
And then מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi says that
it's kosher even
אבא דאבא, abba de-abba, meaning that a grandson can testify against his
grandfather, or vice versa. And the גמרא Gemara tells us ולית הלכתא
ve-leit hilcheta כמר בר רב אשי, ke-Mar bar Rav Ashi, that is
not the הלכה. halacha.
The רשב"ם Rashbam wants to read this as-
he wants to read this as all generations, דבני בנים ובני בני
בנים עד אלף דורות לא יעידו לאבותיהם, de-vnei vanim u-vnei vnei vanim
ad elef dorot lo ya'idu la-avoteihem,
that if you have one line of genealogy, you can never testify
one against another. So no matter how many grandchildren ראובן Reuven has,
those grandsons can never testify against ראובן. Reuven. That's how רשב"ם Rashbam
reads it. However, the רא"ש Rosh disagrees and says it's דווקא davka
שלישי. shelishi.
The grandson cannot testify against the grandfather, but another grandson, so a
great-grandson, could testify against a grandfather. Because at that point you have
רביעי revi'i and once you're at רביעי revi'i according to the ראש,
Rosh, testimony is כשר. kosher. Again, there'll be more, this will be
covered more in depth later on, in the next מסכת, masechet, מסכת
סנהדרין. Masechet Sanhedrin. So that debate is within the same line. That
debate is, right. The question is can a direct descendant ever testify
against his direct antecedent? I guess the right word would be.
The רשב"ם Rashbam says never. The ראש Rosh and he and the
ראש Rosh argues that the רי"ף Rif as well
also holds that a fourth generation can testify against his great-grandfather.
So if there was another generation here,
because this is רביעי revi'i and the relationship is רביעי, revi'i, then
he's כשר kosher according to the ראש. Rosh. Oops. According to the
רשב"ם Rashbam he is not כשר. kosher.
Good? Okay.
ווייטער vaiter in the גמרא, Gemara, that'll be again, that'll be covered
more in depth in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, it gets kind of confusing. So
this is the third ruling, where we are 7, 8, 9, 10,
11, 12, 13 lines down in the גמרא. Gemara. שלח ליה רבי
אבא לרב יוסף בר חמא היה יודע לו בעדות קרקע עד שלא
נסתמא ונסתמא פסול. Shalak lei Rabbi Abba le-Rav Yosef bar Chama: Haya
yodea lo be-edut karka ad shelo nistama ve-nistama pasul. So this ruling
regards someone who knows the dimensions of a field of someone else
and he wants to come to testify about those dimensions. He knew
the dimensions of the field before he went blind and then he
went blind, he is פסול
לעדות. pasul le-edut. ושמואל אמר, Ve-Shmuel amar, שמואל Shmuel says no, כשר
אפשר דמיכוון מצרנהא. kasher efshar de-michvein metzarnaha.
So שמואל Shmuel says he's actually כשר kosher if he was, if
he could see, if he was sighted when he saw the field
initially and now he's blind, he's actually כשר kosher because he can
describe the boundaries of the field, he can say it goes from
such and such tree to that giant rock which I know that
I remember seeing even if he can't actually walk or point to
the dimensions of the field. אבל גלימא לא, Aval glima lo, but
שמואל Shmuel says if he was initially sighted and now he's blind
and he knew the testimony regarding a cloak, he cannot testify regarding
it now that he's blind, because according, because the רשב"ם Rashbam explains,
cloaks are all too similar to one another, he can't describe it
in detail. ורב ששת אמר אפילו גלימא אפשר דמיכוון מידת ארכו ומידת
רחבו אבל ניסכא לא. Ve-Rav Sheshet amar afilu glima efshar de-michvein midat
orko u-midat rochbo aval niska lo. So רב ששת Rav Sheshet says
even, even a coat, if he was initially sighted and now he's
blind he can give testimony on it because he can describe its
length and its width. But a ניסכא, niska, which רשב"ם Rashbam says
is a חתיכת כסף או זהב, chatichat kesef o zahav, it's just
a chunk of, a piece of silver or gold, he cannot give
testimony regarding it. ורב פפא אמר אפילו ניסכא אפשר דמיכוון מידת משקלותיו.
Ve-Rav Papa amar afilu niska efshar de-michvein midat mishkalotav.
Even a piece of gold or silver he can give testimony because
maybe before he was blind he knew how much the piece of
gold weighed, it was a five-ounce piece of gold and that is
good enough testimony to give to say that I know it belonged
to such and such a person.
מיתיבי. Meitvei. So we have now a, is this a משנה? Mishnah?
It's either a משנה Mishnah or ברייתא, Braita, I think it's a
משנה, Mishnah,
that is going to reject all of these.
היה יודע לו בעדות עד שלא נעשה חתנו ונעשה חתנו. Haya yodea
lo be-edut ad shelo na'aseh chosno ve-na'aseh chosno. So he knew testimony
regarding a person but before that person had become his
son-in-law and now he's his son-in-law.
פיקח ונתחרש, Pikeach ve-nitcharesh,
so he was able to see and hear and now he's a
deaf-mute. פיקח ונסתמא, Pikeach ve-nistama, he could see and now he's blind.
שפוי ונשתטה, Shipui ve-nishtateh, he was a sound mind and now he
is, he has gone, he has lost his mind, he's gone crazy,
פסול. pasul. So if he was כשר לעדות kosher le-edut when he
first learned about what he was testifying about
and now he is פסול לעדות, pasul le-edut, whether it's because of
a relationship that's been created through being his,
through marriage or whether he
takes on a condition that makes him פסול לעדות, pasul le-edut, being
blind, being a deaf-mute,
or being crazy, you're פסול לעדות pasul le-edut so it doesn't matter
that he was כשר לעדות kosher le-edut when he first learned about
it. אבל היה יודע לו בעדות, Aval haya yodea lo be-edut, but,
but if he knew about this testimony, עד שלא נעשה חתנו ונעשה
חתנו ומתה בתו. ad shelo na'aseh chosno ve-na'aseh chosno u-meta bito. So
he knew about this testimony, he knew the information, and then he
became שייך shayach to the case through marriage, but then the relation,
his daughter dies, so that he is... no longer the father-in-law of
this man, or פקח ונתחרש וחזר ונתפקח, pikeach venitcheresh vechazar venitpakeach, or
he was, he could see and hear, he could speak and hear,
but then he became a deaf-mute, but then he became seeing and
hearing again, פקח ונסתמא וחזר ונתפקח pikeach venistama vechazar venitpakeach or he
was seeing and then he went blind and then he became sighted
again, שפוי ונשתטה
וחזר ונשתפה, shafui venishtateh vechazar venishtafah,
so he was of sound mind and then he went crazy and
then he went back to being of sound mind, כשר. kasher. He's
כשר. kasher. So even he's כשר kasher at the beginning and he's
כשר kasher at the end, and in between he was in this
state of פסול. pasul. The question is, does that label of being
פסול עדות, pasul edut, does he maintain that status or does he
return to being כשר kasher again? And the ברייתא braita teaches us
here that he's actually כשר. kasher. זה הכלל, zeh haklal, well this
is the general—כל שתחילתו או סופו בפסלות פסול. kol shetechilato o sofo
bepaslut pasul. So if he was פסול לעדות pasul le’edut when he
learned the information, or he's פסול לעדות pasul le’edut when he's giving
the information, he's פסול pasul to give the עדות. edut. תחילתו
וסופו בכשרות כשר, techilato vesofo bechashrut kasher, but if he was כשר
kasher for עדות edut when he learned the information and he's כשר
kasher for עדות edut now that he's giving the information to a
בית דין, beit din, it doesn't matter what happened in between, he's
כשר. kasher. He suggests the ברייתא. braita.
What's that? He suggests the ברייתא. braita. So it's okay.
תיובתא דכולהו תיובתא. tiyuvta dechulhu tiyuvta. So the גמרא Gemara then concludes
on the beginning of קכ״ח עמוד ב׳ kuf chaf chet amud bet
that it is in fact a rejection of all of the previous
opinions that we just saw.
Indeed it is—it is a good refutation.
My question is, how come all of these אמוראים Amoraim didn't know
this ברייתא? braita? I could not find an answer. But the only
person who rules correctly was רבי אבא לרב יוסף Rabbi Abba leRav
Yosef who said that if he knew בעדות, be’edut, if he knew
about the testimony of the field before he became blind and then
he became blind, he's פסול. pasul. So he rules according to this
ברייתא. braita. All the rest of them said that even though he's
blind now, he can be מתכוון mitchaven to
different—he can indicate
different סימנים, simanim, different symbols on what he's testifying about, they said
he was כשר, kasher, but this ברייתא braita rules differently
and rejects all of those opinions. Okay,
top of קכ״ח עמוד ב׳, kuf chaf chet amud bet, the fourth
ruling,
שלח רבי אבא לרב יוסף בר חמא, shalach Rabbi Abba leRav Yosef
bar Chama, once again: האומר על תינוק בין הבנים נאמן, ha’omer al
tinok bein habanim ne’eman, ורבי יוחנן אמר אינו נאמן. veRabbi Yochanan amar
eino ne’eman. It's because we did have one before today. That's what
I thought, there was one before today. I was just noticing today.
Right, I couldn't find it. I thought there was—it's at the end
of the page just before. Right. Right, so the previous ruling was
very much related to what the גמרא Gemara had been talking about
and these are all because it talked about a שלח ליה רבי
אבא לרב יוסף בר חמא, shalach lei Rabbi Abba leRav Yosef bar
Chama, it brings
five—it brings six more
rulings
which are less connected to our סוגיא sugya and it will also
at the end rule on all six of these, I think excluding
that first one that came, which is why I'm counting them the
way that I am.
Also there was a נקודתיים nekudatayim on the page and I know
that's just what the publishers
do.
Yeah.
Okay, so number—what I'm calling number four. שלח רבי אבא לרב יוסף
בר חמא האומר על תינוק בין הבנים נאמן ורבי יוחנן אמר אינו
נאמן. shalach Rabbi Abba leRav Yosef bar Chama ha’omer al tinok bein
habanim ne’eman veRabbi Yochanan amar eino ne’eman. ורבי יוחנן אמר אינו נאמן.
v'Rabbi Yochanan amar eino ne'eman. So a person who says something about
a תינוק tinok that is amongst other children,
רבי אבא Rabbi Abba says that he's believed, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says אינו נאמן, eino ne'eman,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says he is not believed. מאי קאמר, Mai
ka'amar, what is the thing that he was saying? That
this ruling only said he said a thing about a child, what
is it that he was saying? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אביי Abaye
explains הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, האומר
על תינוק בין הבנים יירש כל נכסי נאמן כרבי יוחנן בן ברוקא
ורבי יוחנן אמר אינו נאמן כרבנן. Ha'omer al tinok bein habanim yeresh
kol nechasai ne'eman k'Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka v'Rabbi Yochanan amar eino ne'eman
k'rabbanan. So אביי Abaye explains that he is picking out a תינוק
tinok amongst the other children and saying this child is going to
should inherit everything that I own and he is נאמן ne'eman like
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka says, which if we
look at
רשב"ם Rashbam
why would he not be believed?
So it's according right. So it's the language is weird because it's
נאמן ne'eman and אינו נאמן eino ne'eman and that's going to be
a rejection of אביי Abaye in a moment. But the גמרא Gemara
is saying that this is connected to
a מחלוקת machloket רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka and
the רבנן, rabbanan, which is in the next משנה mishna if you
flip ahead
to ק"ל Kuf Lamed I believe it's ק"ל עמוד א'. Kuf Lamed
Amud Alef.
On ק"ל Kuf Lamed the משנה mishna there says רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקא אומר אם אמר על מי שראוי ליורשו דבריו קיימים ועל מי
שאין ראוי לו ליורשו אין דבריו קיימים. Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka omer
im amar al mi sheraui l'yorsho devarav kayamim v'al mi she'ein raui
lo l'yorsho ein devarav kayamim. So מחלוקת machloket about whether or not
a person can be סותר soter דברי תורה divrei Torah in order
to bequeath his belongings the way that he wants to. According to
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka says, if this person
is ראוי raui to be יורש yoresh him, so say I'm going
to find my תורה Torah chart here. This is ראובן, Reuven,
he has say he has three sons.
I'm not going to draw them, but he has three sons and
he doesn't want any of them to bequeath anything. So he says,
you know
what? שמעון Shimon
is going to
have all my things when I, I can't even think of the
word in English, is going to inherit all my things when I
die. Inherit, thank you, he's going to inherit all my things when
I die. According to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka
that's fine because he is a person who is, if ראובן Reuven
didn't have any kids, he would inherit him. Therefore his דברים devarim
are קיימים. kayamim. The רבנן rabbanan say no, he can't be, he
can't disregard the words of the תורה Torah like that. The תורה
Torah says he has his eldest gets פי שנים pi shnayim and
his other kids get פי אחד. pi echad. Therefore he can't disregard
the words of the תורה Torah like that. In the case with
תינוק, tinok, what's the difficulty? That the תינוק tinok can't inherit or
like what's the, I don't get what's the difficulty. The case is
he's, according to אביי, Abaye, the case is there are a bunch
of kids and he says this kid is my kid, a random
kid, this is my kid and he gets to inherit all
of my things. According to אביי, Abaye, it's this מחלוקת machloket between
רבי אבא Rabbi Abba and רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. That he can't
be סותר soter דברי תורה divrei Torah according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan and רבנן. rabbanan. According to רבי אבא Rabbi Abba he can
be סותר soter the words of the תורה Torah and he can
give everything to שמעון Shimon even though he has kids that could
inherit. Or to a תינוק? tinok? Or to, oh right, so I
was giving the example above, but say he had five kids and
he says my second son is going to get all of my
things. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say no, he can't be סותר
soter דברי תורה divrei Torah like that, therefore everyone inherits like they
would according to the תורה. Torah. According to רבי אבא Rabbi Abba
and according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka he
can do that and so his second son can get everything as
an inheritance. Meaning not distribute, he wants it not to distribute equally
amongst his sons, he wants he doesn't, right, he doesn't want to
do it like the תורה Torah says. The תורה Torah says פי
שנים, pi shnayim, right, the תורה Torah says פי שנים pi shnayim
to the eldest and everybody else gets equal. He's saying that's not
how I want to do it, I want to do it differently.
And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and the רבנן rabbanan say he can't
do that and רבי אבא Rabbi Abba and רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא
Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka say that he can. Yeah. You were suggesting
yesterday that he could use a different phrasing, he could gift exactly,
beforehand and that way circumvent exactly, that's another solution is that because
you can give gifts when you're alive. So he could just give
a gift. So if you use the right phrasing then he can
do that if he wants. But again that's not, you're not being
in that case you're not being סותר soter דברי תורה divrei Torah
because you're giving it as a gift and not as an inheritance.
It's just a way of getting around
that. What was the root of סותר soter that you used? What
is that? Oh סותר? soter? To
contradict. Contradict, thank you. Yeah. ס samekh ת tav ר resh is
the
שורש, shoresh, it's
the root. Okay. מתקיף לה Matkif lah רבא Rava *Matkif
la Rava*. So רבא Rava *Rava* says back to אביי *Abaye* who
just said that, האי נאמן ואינו נאמן *hai neeman veeino
neeman*. The teaching that רבי אבא Rabbi Abba, *Rabbi Abba* brought uses
the language of נאמן ואינו נאמן *neeman veeino neeman*. If it is,
if the ruling is about what you want to say it is
about, יירש ולא יירש מבעי ליה *yeirash velo yeirash mibayei*, should have
been they inherit or they don't inherit. Right? This is sort of
I think what what you were saying is that the word, the
language doesn't really work. נאמן *neeman*, what do you mean נאמן *neeman*?
We're saying his words are not, his words don't have any effect
on reality. Right? נאמן *neeman* is not the right, believed is not
the right language for that case. If ראובן Reuven *Reuven* was going
to say my second son inherits all my things, I wouldn't say
he's not believed in that case, I would say that person doesn't
inherit the way that he wants to. So the language doesn't pan
out.
Instead, says רבא Rava *Rava*, מבעי ליה אלא אמר רבא Rava הכי
קאמר *mibayei
ela amar Rava hachi kaamar*, this is what the person was saying
about the תינוק בין הבנים *tinok bein habanim*, the baby or the
child among the other children. האומר על תינוק בין הבנים בכורי הוא
נאמן כרבי יהודה ורבי יוחנן אמר אינו נאמן כרבנן *haomer al tinok
bein habanim bechori hu neeman keRabbi Yehuda veRabbi Yochanan amar eino neeman
keRabbanan*. So רבי
אבא Rabbi Abba *Rabbi Abba* says that the person who says this
is my eldest son is believed, which was the same story, like
I mean, it's like a different case. Right? It's a totally different
case and it actually makes sense to say נאמן *neeman*. And this
was a מחלוקת machloket *machloket* we already saw. If we have a
חזקה chazaka *chazakah*, if we have an established,
if we have established that ראובן *Reuven* is someone's eldest son and
he comes along and says no, שמעון *Shimon* is actually my eldest
son, according to רבי אבא Rabbi Abba, *Rabbi Abba* he is believed,
which was what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda* said in the
מחלוקת machloket *machloket* that we already saw on the previous דף *daf*,
and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* says he's not, which was
what the רבנן Rabbanan *Rabbanan* said on the previous דף *daf* in
מחלוקת machloket. *machloket* with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*. That is
the end of the fourth ruling. The fifth ruling. שלח shalach, ליה
רבי אבא Rabbi Abba לרב יוסף בר חמא האומר תיטול אשתי כאחד
מן הבנים נוטלת כאחד מן הבנים *shelach lei Rabbi Abba leRav Yosef
bar Chama haomer titol ishti keechad min habanim notellet keechad min habanim*.
אמר רבא Rava ובנכסים
של עכשיו ובבנים הבאים לאחר מכאן *amar Rava uvenichasim shel achshav uvubanim
habaim leachar mikan*. A person who says my wife once I die
should inherit my properties just as if she is one of my
children,
she does so. So he has five kids and he says also
I want my wife to inherit just like the rest of my
kids, then his his property is split into six parts instead, or
it would be seven parts instead of six parts because of the
פי שנים *pi shenayim* for the בכור *bechor*. So she she basically
counts as one of the kids once he dies. רבא Rava
*Rava* comes along to clarify this ruling. ובנכסים של עכשיו *uvenichasim shel
achshav*, that it is he's talking about the things that he has
right now and anything that comes from now until he dies, anymore
property he gains is not part of this inheritance. So you have
to put an asterisk, you have to like underline the bottom line
for that year and say okay he had twenty-five thousand whatever that
year and that's what gets split up to his wife. Anything from
here until he dies is inherited regularly amongst the rest of his
sons. ובבנים הבאים לאחר
מכאן *uvubanim habaim leachar mikan*, and any subsequent children that are
born or if any of his children die between now and the
time he dies, it's however many kids there are when he dies
is how it's split up. So even if he has when he
makes this statement he has five kids and then by the time
he dies he has seven, it's split up between the seven plus
his wife and not just the five. She gets the same amount
she would get
according to him having seven kids and not according to him having
five kids like he was did when he made his statement. Interesting
that they're distinguishing between the two. Right? On one hand it's it's
right how much property he has when he makes the statement versus
how many kids he has when he dies. The רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*,
רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* explains why that is because he can say because
he's saying תיטול אשתי כאחד מן הבנים *titol ishti keechad min habanim*,
he's he's talking about the property he has right now because he
doesn't know what property he's going to have going forward. And he
doesn't know how many kids he's going to have. He doesn't. He
says ואפילו רבי מאיר *vaafilu Rabbi Meir*, the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says
even according to רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* who says אדם מקנה *adam
makneh* that a person can give something to someone else even if
he doesn't own it yet, but you can only do that if
you expressly say she should inherit just like my kids even for
things that I'm going to acquire later on, and he doesn't say
that here. However for the בנים *banim*, because he says because he
knows he's talking about when he dies, the assumption is that
however many kids he has when he dies is how many בנים
*banim* he's going to be it's going to be split. Right? Because
he says כאחד מן הבנים *keechad min habanim*. So however many kids
I have when I die, that's how my property is going to
be split up. Therefore my wife... Okay, moving on to the sixth
and final ruling. This one is a little
bit longer. Anyone know the הלכה Halacha *halacha* on that, like let's
say somebody wants to go against...
We're going to get at the end, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* rules
on all of these rulings. שלח ליה רבי אבא Rabbi Abba לרב
יוסף בר חמא
*Shelach lei Rabbi Abba leRav Yosef bar Chama*: המוציא שטר shtar חוב
על חבירו *Hamotzi shtar chov al chaveiro*, מלווה אומר *malveh omer* לא
נפרעתי כלום *lo nifrati klum*, ולווה אומר *veloveh omer* פרעתי מחצה *parati
mechetza*, והעדים *veha'eidim*... okay, stop there. Someone brings forward a document that
says, a document of debt, and says: This person owes me money.
The debtor says he hasn't paid me anything... wait, the debtor is
the person who owes the money. The loaner says he hasn't paid
me anything. The debtor says: No, I paid half, I paid half
of it. והעדים מעידים שפרע כולו *veha'eidim me'idim shepara kulo*, but there
are witnesses who say he paid back the whole thing. הרי זה
נשבע וגובה מחצה מנכסים בני חורין אבל ממשועבדים לא *Harei zeh nishba
vegoveh mechetza minechasim benei chorin aval mimishubadin lo*. So in this case,
he takes a שבועה shvuah. *shevuah*, he takes an oath that he
says that he has paid half of it, and then the other
half is paid back from unencumbered property, which is property that he
still owns and not that he either, not property that has a
lien on it for other loans and not property that he has
sold. So only property that he owns and does not have a
lien on, unencumbered property. אבל ממשועבדים לא *Aval mimishubadin lo*, so anything
that has been sold to someone else or anything that has a
lien on it, he cannot pay it back. דאמרי *De'amri*, because the
owners of that property or those who have a lien on that
property because of their loans will say: אנן אעדים סמכינן *Anan a'eidim
samchinan*. We relied on the witnesses to assume that he had paid
everything back, and therefore we bought this property thinking, under the assumption
that this person does not have any loans. So it can't be
paid back from that property. So just a quick review of what,
why he would be נשבע *nishba*. So רשב"ם Rashbam. *Rashbam* says in
the one, two, three, four, five, six, seven lines down in the
widest lines of the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*: והעדים מעידים *veha'eidim me'idim*. So
the witnesses come and say he paid back the whole thing, אחר
דהודה מחצה *achar dehodah mechetza*, he has already said: I have paid
back half of it. נשבע *Nishba*, says רשב"ם Rashbam? *Rashbam*, הלווה שפרע
*haloveh shepara*. So the person who took the loan takes an oath
that he has paid back half of it, ויפטר מלשלם מחצה *veyipater
milishalem mechetza*, and he is פטור *patur*, he is exempt from paying
the half that he has sworn about. ומחצה ישלם לפי שכבר הודה
דהודאת בעל דין שוה יותר מהעדותם *Umechetza yishalem lefi shekevar hodah dehodat
ba'al din shaveh yoteir meha'edutam*. So the person, the reason that he
pays it back half, even though there are עדים eidim. *eidim* who
say he paid back the whole thing, is because his word is
believed more than the witnesses' words, because he has already admitted that
he's paid back half of it. And the תורה *Torah* tells us
that when someone owes money and he is מודה *modeh*, he agrees
that he still owes part of it, he takes an oath that
he paid back the part that he claimed to and he pays
back the rest out of his money. If he denies that he
has paid, if he says: I still owe the whole thing, then
he does not take a שבועה shvuah, *shevuah*, and he says, or
if he says: I paid back the whole thing, there's no oath
taken. So because he has acknowledged that he still owes part of
the loan, he has to take a שבועה shvuah *shevuah*. Even though
you have עדים eidim *eidim*. Even though you have עדים eidim *eidim*.
Negative עדות edut *eidut* also is stronger than their, meaning, you're saying:
I paid back half and I didn't pay back half, that עדות
*eidut* that he didn't pay back half is stronger than... his עדות
*eidut*, right, his עדות *eidut* that he has not paid it back
is stronger than the עדים eidim, *eidim* who say he paid back
the whole thing. Just presumably he has better knowledge. Right, and he
said it before the עדים edim, *eidim* came up. So he was
presumably telling the truth about it before the עדים edim *eidim* came,
because if he had paid back the whole thing, he would have
said: I paid back the whole thing, and then the עדים edim
*eidim* come and would have confirmed that. But because he said only
half and then the עדים eidim *eidim* came... So he's basically exposed
those עדים *eidim*? It's a good question. Probably not. I guess we
just ignore them because he has to, because according to this, the
case would be the same regardless of whether or not the עדים
*eidim* are there. Right? If they're false witnesses. So the alright the
נפקא מינא for that, the implications of that would be can they
become, can they be witnesses again? And I don't know what I
don't know what the דינא dina of that is. That's a good
question. I don't think the רשב''ם Rashbam even brings that up. So
I didn't see anything about that. Okay, so then the this ruling
goes on to say, ואי מודה דאמרינן סהדינן, ve'i modeh de'amrinan sahadeinan,
okay so ואפילו לרבי עקיבא דאמר משיב אבידה הוי. va'afillu le'Rabbi Akiva
de'amar meshiv aveidah havei. So and this is according to even according
to Rabbi Akiva. This was a מחלוקת machlokes at the beginning of
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia on the I think on דף ג. daf
gimmel. The רשב''ם Rashbam it'll be helpful to just read this inside
the רשב''ם Rashbam. because he summarizes it very well. ואפילו לרבי עקיבא
דאמר va'afillu le'Rabbi Akiva de'amar is the דיבור המתחיל. dibur hamatchil. התם
hatam over there in sorry go up one, two, three lines. My
printing has a little two dots inside the רשב''ם. The line starts
to פרה הכל. parah hakol. פלוגתא דרבי עקיבא ורבי שמעון בר אלעזר
בתחילת שנים אוחזין. plugta de'Rabbi Akiva ve'Rabbi Shimon bar Elazar bit'chillat Shnayim
Ochazin. So this is a מחלוקת between Rabbi Akiva and and Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar at the beginning of שנים אוחזין, Shnayim Ochazin, שטר
שכתוב בו סלעים או דינרים, shtar shekatuv bo sela'im o dinarim, מלוה
אומר חמש ולוה אומר שלוש. malveh omer chamesh veloveh omer shalosh. So
you have the the person who gave the loan brings forth a
שטר shtar that just said I loaned multiple coins to this person.
The person who took the loan, the debtor, says I borrowed three
and the person who gave the loan says I gave him five.
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר הואיל והודה מקצת הטענה ישבע, Rabbi Shimon
ben Elazar omer ho'il vehodeh miktzat hata'anah yishava, because he said for
he said I owe three, he's like a person he's like a
מודה מקצת modeh miktzat and therefore he has to take a an
oath. So he's like someone who has acknowledged part of the loan
but not the whole loan and has to take an oath. Rabbi
Akiva says because אינו אלא כמשיב אבידה, eino ella kimeshiv aveidah, he's
like someone who's returning lost property and does not have to take
a שבועה. shvuah Why? Because the שטר shtar said סלעים, sela'im, right?
The שטר shtar just said coins, which means that the minimum number
of coins that it could be is two. Because he says I
borrowed three, he's like a משיב אבידה meshiv aveidah because he could
have just claimed, it's kind of like a מיגו, migo, he could
have just claimed I owe two coins and it would have been
the whole thing. But because he has acknowledged the thing that he
owes three, he's believed that he owes three and he's like someone
returning lost property in that he does not have to take any
kind of oath that he however on the amount of money that
he owns. And then why would somebody write a document like that?
It's a bad idea. Yeah, if you go to the effort of
writing a document, you should write how many coins. Exactly. It's not
a very good loan document in that case. Certainly nowadays that would
we have a lot more detail in our loan documents than that.
So according to the גמרא Gemara then, according sorry according to רבי
אבא, Rabbi Abba even Rabbi Akiva ואפילו לרבי עקיבא va'afillu le'Rabbi Akiva
who says that he's like a משיב אבידה meshiv aveidah in that
case and he does not have to take a שבועה, shvuah in
our case even Rabbi Akiva would say that he has to take
a שבועה shvuah and he would agree with רבי אבא Rabbi Abba
who said he has to take an oath. Why? הני מילי היכא
דליכא עדים, hani milei heicha deleika eidim, because Rabbi Akiva's case was
where there were no עדים. So it was just where the שטר
shtar came forward and said I loan him coins, the person says
yes I owe him three coins, he's like a משיב אבידה. meshiv
aveidah. But if there are עדים then it's a different case and
he would have to take a loan, he sorry he would have
to take an oath. הני מילי היכא דליכא עדים אבל היכא דאיכא
עדים אירטוטי אירטט. hani milei heicha deleika eidim aval heicha de'ika eidim
irtutei irtat. He has the fear of the עדים upon him and
therefore he would have to take an oath. What does אירטוטי אירטט
irtutei irtat mean? The רשב''ם explains איכא עדים כאחד מהם. eika eidim
ke'echad mehem. He knows that there are עדים, he knows that there
are witnesses that are going to confirm one of their opinions but
he doesn't know which. איכא למימר דזה הלווה היודע שרוצים להעיד כאחד
מהם. eika lemeimar de'zeh haloveh hayodeia sherotzim leha'id ke'echad mehem. He knows
that they want to give testimony to confirm one of their words.
ואירטט שלא יבואו לסייע למלווה לפי ההודאה מחצה. ve'irtat shelo yavo'u lesayeia
lemalveh lefi hahoda'ah mechetza. He was afraid, he knew that there were
witnesses, he didn't know who they were going to confirm like, therefore
he says to hedge his bets he says I'm going to say
that I owe three coins. because then he knows that he would
only have to pay back three coins. Right, if the witnesses were
to come along, if he were to say I owe two, and
the witnesses said he owes five, then he would have to pay
back all five. But because when he says I owe back three
coins, he has the מיגו migo of the minimum of two, he
knows that if he says he owes three, then he only has
to pay back three. So because there are עדים, we assume that
because he's afraid of what they're going to testify, he said three,
and not because he's being honest. Does that make sense? So we're
assuming that this is the same case with what we just read
about in the רשב"ם? Exactly. In the שטר shtar is ambiguous? Yes,
exactly. And so he knows there are witnesses. They're going to come
along. He says, they could testify according to me that I only
owe two coins, or they could testify according to my to the
loan, the guy who gave me the loan that I owe five.
Therefore, I'm going to say I owe three because then I only
have to pay back three as opposed to taking the risk that
they're going to testify according to the according to the... So do
we believe him for three in that case? In that case, according
to רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba even according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
he has to take a שבועה shvuah and pay it back because
he is מודה במקצת. modeh b'miktzat. Which I guess means he would
have to pay back so we learned about מיגו, migo, מיגו migo
versus עדים in the witnesses versus מיגו. migo. Right, is a מיגו
migo believed if there are witnesses to say the other thing? I
guess here it's not. I forget what the though. Yeah, I don't
remember either. But I do remember that מחלוקת. But if the witnesses
wholly supported the lender, then probably we would trust the witnesses over
the מיגו, migo, right? Say that again? If the witnesses supported the
lender, that it was really five, if the witnesses supported the lender
that it's really five, then yeah, what this is saying, what רבי
אבא Rabbi Abba here is saying that even in that case, he
has to take a שבועה shvuah. and pay back all five. He's
not believed to say it was only three. The witnesses are believed.
So then we don't need a שבועה shvuah if we're going to
just let the witnesses trump, and his שבועה shvuah is a meaningless
שבועה. shvuah, No, because he has to take a שבועה shvuah. that
he already paid back the three. Right, he's claiming I've already paid
some back. He's saying I paid back it's two different issues, right?
One is how much was the loan to begin with, and that's
where the שטר just says coins, you don't know how many the
original loan was. That's different from everybody agrees it was five coins
to start with and the issue is how much did he pay
back. You're right. That's my fault. We know how much the loan
was in this case. What we don't know is how much he's
paid. The witnesses say he paid back the whole thing. He says
I paid back half. He takes a שבועה shvuah to say he
paid back half and pays back the rest. Even רבי אבא Rabbi
Abba says even according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, who in that
case where we don't know how much the loan was, he's like
a משיב אבידה. meshiv aveidah. In our case, he's not like someone
returning lost property because of the because of the fear of the
witnesses. He knows there are witnesses that are going to come along.
He doesn't know who they're going to testify like. They could say
they could come along and say he hasn't paid back anything. They
could come along and say he's paid back the whole thing. And
he doesn't know which. Therefore, he claims I paid back half in
order to hedge his bets. Because he knows that if they come
along and say he paid back the whole thing, he wouldn't have
to pay back anything, which is why the law is that he
actually does have to we rely on what he originally said and
not what the witnesses say. Okay. Good? Good. Okay. מתקיף לה אמר
רב אשי. amar Rav Ashi. רב אשי Rav Ashi disagrees with this
what even according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. אדרבה, Adaraba, the opposite,
אפילו רבי שמעון בן אלעזר afillu Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar דאמר מודה
מקצת הטענה d'amar modeh miktzat hatanah הני מילי hanei milei even according
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who was חולק cholek on רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and said that in the case in בבא מציעא, Bava
Metzia, he is a he's someone who's מודה על מקצת modeh al
miktzat and therefore has to take a שבועה, shvuah. he's someone who
acknowledges that he still owes part of the loan but has paid
back half and therefore has to take a שבועה. shvuah In our
case, even according to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar,
דמודה מקצת הטענה, d'modeh miktzat hatanah, הני מילי, hanei milei, he was
only talking about היכא דליכא סהדי. heicha d'leika sahadei. He was talking
about a case where there were no סהדי sahadei דקמסייע ליה, d'kamsaya
leh, that there were no סהדי sahadei that would confirm what he
said. אבל היכא דאיכא סהדי Aval heicha d'ika sahadei דקמסייע ליה, d'kamsaya
leh, ודאי משיב אבידה הוי. vadai meshiv aveidah havei. In our case,
where there are סהדי, sahadei, he is in fact Right, so he
says I paid back half the loan, the witnesses come along and
say he paid back the whole loan. According to מר בר רב
אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi *Mar bar Rav Ashi*, he's like a
משיב אבידה meshiv aveidah. *meshiv aveidah*. So technically the or the witnesses
are partially believed to exempt the debtor from taking an oath and
instead he just has to pay back the rest of the loan,
but he's like someone returning lost property and not like someone paying
back half a debt. And therefore he does not have to take
an oath, yeah. But is is there's a confusion here because you're
saying that the borrower may have made that admission because he was
concerned the witnesses were going to testify against him. Right. He doesn't
really know what's going to happen until they testify. Right. So now
they testify in his favor and we're reversing what his being requested
of the borrower, you follow what I'm saying? You know, he still
has to pay back half in he was מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat,
*modeh b'mikzat*. In terms of a square? In terms of the שבועה
*shavuah*, in terms of the שבועה *shavuah* we say he does not
have to swear. Right. And it's because we take swearing very seriously.
So if there are witnesses who say he paid back the whole
thing, then taking an oath against those witnesses would be risky because
it might we have עדים *edim* who who are suggesting that that
would be a false oath if he says I only paid back
half as opposed to saying I paid back the whole thing. But
you said before he had to take an oath because the reasoning
that you explained in terms of Rabbi Akiva was because he was
concerned that the witnesses might testify against him, right? So he had
to take an oath, right? Because it might not have been his
true he might not have been speaking honestly, he might just have
been speaking fearfully. Right. So now but he doesn't know that they're
going to come and and speak in his favor. Right, he doesn't
know what they're going to say. Right. So now they came and
spoke in his favor, we're changing our view of why he said
what he said is what I... Yeah. So the question I think
the question is what is the assumption we make about the debtor
in this case? Is the assumption he knows there are עדים *edim*
who are going to come, according to the רשב"א *Rashba*, he knows
there are עדים *edim* or going to come give testimony. He doesn't
know what they're going to say, if he owes or doesn't owe.
Is do we assume that the debtor is going to hedge his
bets on the with the pro- assuming that the עדים *edim* are
going to testify against him, or is he going to hedge his
bets the other way that he's in fact going to say he
paid back half risking if he say he's going to pay back
half hoping that the עדים *edim* will come and testify for him?
So it's which right which way of the risk is right what's
his risk assessment? Why would he testify at all if he thought
they if he really believed they're coming to testify the witnesses will
come in his favor, then he wouldn't even have to pay anything,
right? Because they would say he paid it in full. You're right.
So then if he was hedging his bets that way he would
just say I paid back the whole thing. So I'm sensing some
confusion. Right, there is it's so maybe even so we would say
the fear of the witnesses was on him and that's why he
said he paid back half, but the reason that he doesn't have
to take a שבועה *shavuah* is because we have is because we
have עדים *edim* that say he paid back the whole thing. Therefore
we don't want to make him take a שבועה *shavuah*. So this
seems to be more about the שבועה *shavuah* than about the so
מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi *Mar bar Rav Ashi*
is saying not he's saying yes, I agree with you that אייתו
אייתו *eitu eitu*, that he's worried about what the witnesses are going
to come say, but once the witnesses come along and testify in
his favor, we shouldn't make we don't have to make him take
a שבועה *shavuah* because now he is like a someone returning lost
property and not like a debtor because we have witnesses who say
he paid back the whole thing. Therefore he should not take a
שבועה *shavuah*. And is it also not a little strange that we're
basing the whole thing on witnesses who say he paid back the
whole thing when the question is, you know, did he pay back
three? You know what I'm saying? In other words they're we're sort
of right we're only we're half half relying on the witnesses, but
not fully relying on the witnesses because we say I think because
we take שבועה *shavuah* because we take oaths so seriously, we don't
want to make him take an oath that he paid back half
because we have witnesses saying he paid back the whole thing. So
we're basically saying take what is possibly a false oath in order
to make sure everything's okay when we have we don't want to
say that, right? You follow that about the oath. Okay. Yeah. Yeah.
But we still believe them and what to make him pay back.
Right, we part right we only partially believe them basically is what
we're saying. And this is instances where you sort of split the
belief of the testimony. Absolutely. So I'm not sure this is unique
that because usually it's like two different statements that are... It happened
right, it happens in other places, but also in those places it's
a little bit it's a little bit right going both ways. Okay,
so we're almost at the end here. So that is the last
of the six rulings and now we're going to rule on what
how we פוסקין pasken, on all six of those rulings. דרש מר
זוטרא משמיה דרב שימי בר אשי. Darash Mar Zutra mishmeih de-Rav Shimi
bar Ashi. מר זוטרא Mar Zutra said the following expounded the following
in the name of רב שימי בר אשי, Rav Shimi bar Ashi,
הלכתא בכל הני שמעתתא כי דשלח ליה רבי אבא לרב יוסף בר
חמא. Hilcheta bechol hani shema'ateta kide'shalach lei Rabbi Abba l'Rav Yosef bar
Chama. The הלכה Halacha? is like רבי אבא Rabbi Abba sent to
רב יוסף Rav Yosef in all of these cases. אמר ליה רבינא
לרב אשי, Amar lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi, דרבי נחמן מאי? de-Rabbi Nachman
mai? In the case of רבי נחמן, Rabbi Nachman, what is the
הלכה? Halacha In our first שלח, we had actually we'll just read
it. דרבי נחמן מאי de-Rabbi Nachman mai says רשב"ם דפליג עליה גבי
עבדים, depalig alei gabei avadim, right? In our first case, רב נחמן
Rav Nachman disagreed with the ruling of רבי אבא Rabbi Abba that
he sent, that רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said you can pay back
with עדים and רב נחמן Rav Nachman said you cannot pay back
with עבדים. avadim. What's the הלכה Halacha there? Because usually we say
that the הלכה Halacha. in these kinds of cases is like רב
נחמן. Rav Nachman. אמר ליה אין גובין. Amar lei ein govin. אין
גובין מתנינן לה וכן אמר רב נחמן. ein govin matninan lah ve-chein
amar Rav Nachman. רב אשי Rav Ashi says oh the way we
taught it originally was incorrect. What רבי אבא Rabbi Abba actually sent
was what רבי אבא Rabbi Abba actually sent was you cannot pay
back those loans using עבדים avadim and רב נחמן Rav Nachman agrees
and therefore that's the הלכה. Halacha ואלא הלכתא לאפוקי מאי? Ve-ella hilcheta
le-apukei mai? Okay so then why do we have to say הלכתא,
hilcheta, הלכתא? hilcheta? All of these cases were sent from רבי אבא
Rabbi Abba to רב נחמן בר יוסף Rav Nachman bar Yosef and
none of them had any dissenting opinion. So why are you telling
me that the הלכה Halacha is like them? It seems pretty straightforward.
אי לאפוקי מדרבא מוסיפו. Ee le-apukei mide-Rava mosifu. If it is to
say that the הלכה Halacha was like רבי אבא Rabbi Abba. and
not like רבא Rava in the case where רבא Rava said in
our עדות case regarding relatives where רב נחמן Rav Nachman said sorry
where רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said אפילו שלישי בשני afilu shelishi be-sheni
and then רבא Rava said אפילו שלישי בראשון afilu shelishi be-rishon דאמר
אף בראשון, de-amar af be-rishon, right? רבא Rava said אף בראשון af
be-rishon that the שלישי shelishi can testify even against his grandfather's brother.
What רבא Rava was saying was not to disagree with the ruling
of רבי אבא Rabbi Abba, but rather was clarifying his ruling. רבי
אבא Rabbi Abba sent that the שלישי shelishi can testify against the
שני sheni and רבא said he was only saying that to disagree
with someone who explicitly said שלישי shelishi cannot testify against שני. sheni.
רבי אבא Rabbi Abba was saying no he can testify against שני.
sheni. רבא says and he even holds that the שלישי shelishi can
testify against the ראשון. rishon. So not that it was a disagreement,
it was a clarification is basically what he's saying. Therefore the הלכה
Halacha is like רבא is like רבא agreeing with רבי אבא. רבי
אבא agrees with רבא and רבא was just further clarifying his opinion.
The רשב"ם there explains it pretty well. He brings or rather he
just summarizes the case there. I don't think we have time to
get into it at this moment. אי דמר בר רב אשי Ee
mide-Mar bar Rav Ashi who said דאכשר באבא דאבא הא כבר אפסיק
דלית הלכתא כוותיה, de-achshar be-abba de-abba ha kevar afsik de-leit hilcheta kevataih,
says רשב"ם. If it's like מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav
Ashi who said this is the same case of the testimony, מר
בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi said that a great-grandson cannot
מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi said a great-grandson can
wait yeah a great-grandson can testify against his grandfather. The גמרא Gemara
already told us the הלכה Halacha. is not like that. No, sorry,
I said that wrong. מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi
said a grandson can testify against his grandfather. The גמרא Gemara already
told us that's not the הלכה. Halacha So you don't have to
פוסקין, who is this again? מר זוטרא Mar Zutra doesn't have to
tell me that because the הלכה Halacha. was already established that it's
not the הלכה. halacha אי לאפוקי... Ee le-apukei... אלא פוקי מדשמואל, Ela
pukei mideShmuel, if it's to say the הלכה halacha is not like
שמואל Shmuel who said ורב ששת בר רב פפא, veRav Sheshet bar
Rav Pappa, sorry. אלא פוקי מדשמואל ורב ששת בר רב פפא Ela
pukei mideShmuel veRav Sheshet bar Rav Pappa who were all talking about
the witness, what someone who is blind can testify about. הא איתותבו,
Ha itutvu, right? We already we already saw that we had a
ברייתא braita that said they're all wrong. So you don't have to
פסקן pasken for that, you don't have to פסקן pasken that from
me. אלא פוקי מדרבי יוחנן, Ela pukei mideRabbi Yochanan, rather to say
that the הלכה halacha was not like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan דאמר
אינו נאמן כרבנן de'amar eino ne'eman keRabbanan who said that a person
is not believed to tell us who his eldest son is against
the חזקה chazaka of his eldest son. That was the case where
ראובן says he has five kids and he says this one is
my eldest son, even though we have it established that a different
one is the eldest son. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said he's not
believed, so we're now saying the הלכה halacha is that in fact
he is believed against רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. and against the רבנן
and in favor of רבי אבא, which no, like רבי יהודה. So
we פסקן pasken like רבי יהודה there who says that he is
believed against the חזקה about who his eldest son is. Which, can
you tell me with the language here, אלא פוקי מדשמואל ורב ששת
בר רב פפא איתותבו. Ela pukei mideShmuel veRav Sheshet bar Rav Pappa
itutvu. אלא פוקי, Ela pukei, so we're not talking about the third
the third case, we're talking about the fourth case. And there's two
or there's like this... We are not talking about the third case
because we already had a תיובתא דכולהו תיובתא tiuvta dechulhu tiuvta at
the top of קכ"ז עמוד ב'. Kuf Chaf Zayin Amud Bet. So
our topic at, we're not talking we're not talking about... it can't
be אלא פוקי ela pukei the third case because that's not... why,
how come, how come מר זוטרא Mar Zutra had to tell me
הלכה כרבי אבא שלח, halacha keRabbi Abba shelach, right? In each case
there's either not a מחלוקת or we already ruled in the גמרא
what the הלכה halacha is. So you don't have to come and
tell, right, in one case we had a ברייתא braita that was
a תיובתא tiuvta to all of them. In this case, we already
ruled on all of them basically is what it's saying. But we
did not rule in the case of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan, So
we're saying it's not the הלכה halacha is not like רבי יוחנן,
it's in fact like רבי אבא who said he is believed. ומידי
דאיתקשתא גמרא במר בר רב אשי, U-mide-itkasta Gemara beMar bar Rav Ashi,
and to say that we do not פסקן pasken like the objection
of מר בר רב אשי which we just saw at the bottom
of קכ"ז עמוד ב' Kuf Chaf Zayin Amud Bet that... the question
of whether or not he has to take a שבועה or whether
he is, whether he's like a מודה במקצת, whether he's like someone
who is who agrees that he owes part of a loan or
whether he's like a משיב אבידה. meshiv aveidah, מר בר רב אשי
wanted to say he's like a משיב אבידה, רבי אבא wanted to
say he's like someone who has to take a שבועה. The הלכה
is that in that case when there are when he says he
paid back half and there are עדים who say he paid back
the whole thing, he in fact has to take a שבועה and
has to pay back the rest of the loan. We will stop
here for today.